<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>legal positivism on Value Thing</title>
    <link>https://value-thing.github.io/tags/legal-positivism/</link>
    <description>Value Thing (legal positivism)</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 28 Oct 2020 00:00:00 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
    <atom:link href="https://value-thing.github.io/tags/legal-positivism/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Norms fetishism</title>
      <link>https://value-thing.github.io/post/normsfetishism/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 Oct 2020 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://value-thing.github.io/post/normsfetishism/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I want to focus on two aspects of norms writ-large (e.g., legal norms, social norms, etc…) in order to tease out some implications about the fetishism of norms (i.e.,  objective norms that appear as naturalized entities) [1]:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A norm’s &lt;em&gt;purchase&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A norm’s &lt;em&gt;efficacy&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;!-- more --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although I think the question of whether these aspects are necessary and/or sufficient conditions for being a norm is interesting, the focus of this post does not hinge on this. Regardless of their status as necessary and/or sufficient conditions, I think these concepts are useful for assessing how norms &lt;em&gt;function&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;purchase-and-efficacy&#34;&gt;Purchase and efficacy&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Purchase&lt;/strong&gt; refers to a norm’s &lt;em&gt;grip&lt;/em&gt; within the context that it is intended to be applied. This grip can be the result of a many number of things, often in combination, such as community interest and/or some form of enforcement.  Purchase amounts to a norm’s recognition as a norm and it comes in degrees.  If a norm has both legal enforcement and community recognition (positive or negative) it has a &lt;em&gt;stronger&lt;/em&gt;  grip than if the norm was simply enforced.  While some legal norms are enforceable, often times it seems as if community recognition of  these norms &lt;em&gt;as norms&lt;/em&gt; is generally sufficient to guarantee the grip of norms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Efficacy&lt;/strong&gt; refers to the fact that a norm makes a practical difference. So, if the norm did not exist, there would be no practical difference within the context of its application. What I mean by “practical difference” requires some unpacking.  As a start, we can say that if a norm makes a practical difference, it allows us to &lt;em&gt;do something&lt;/em&gt; that would otherwise not be possible.  Some theorists argue that norms &lt;em&gt;allow us&lt;/em&gt; to bypass lengthy deliberation on questions that have been more-or-less &amp;ldquo;settled.&amp;rdquo; For example, in his book &lt;em&gt;Legality&lt;/em&gt; (2011), Scott Shapiro argues,
&amp;gt;Unless the community has a way of reducing the costs and risks of
planning, resolving these moral problems will be, at best, expensive and,
at worst, impossible. On the Planning Theory, the fundamental aim of
the law is to meet this moral demand in an efficient manner. By providing
a highly nimble and durable method of social planning, the law enables
communities to solve the numerous and serious problems that
would otherwise be too costly or risky to resolve. (213)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While norms are a broader category than law––not to mention that, strictly speaking, Shapiro views laws as “plans” and I do not agree with his overall view––this characterization can be &lt;em&gt;mutatis mutandis&lt;/em&gt; applied to norms writ-large. This is the aspect of efficacy that I will focus on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-flexible-normness-of-norms&#34;&gt;The flexible normness of norms&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At first glance, purchase and efficacy seem to go hand-in-hand. If a norm has a &lt;em&gt;grip&lt;/em&gt;, then it must also &lt;em&gt;do something&lt;/em&gt;, right? Not necessarily.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Imagine that you are living in a community where drinking alcohol in a public park without a special permit (e.g., an event permit) is illegal.  Let’s say that when the local softball league uses the public park for their tournaments, the players drink alcohol without a permit. While they take measures to disguise their drinks, it is common knowledge––even in law-enforcement––that the players are, in fact, drinking alcohol &lt;em&gt;illegally&lt;/em&gt;.  Despite this, the rule is not enforced and generally, aside from the occasional complaint, the community is fine with it. In this case, the norm is &lt;em&gt;efficacious&lt;/em&gt; in the sense that norm leaves no question that the players are doing something illegal (i.e., going against a legal norm). Although one may debate the legitimacy of the norm, no one needs to deliberate whether or not these actions are, in fact, illegal.  However, in this case, &lt;em&gt;the norm seems to lack purchase&lt;/em&gt;: the community and law enforcement are more-or-less fine with disregarding the norm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A norm with purchase, but no efficacy is more difficult, but not impossible, to conceive. Imagine, as some do, that in making decisions about the applicability of a norm in a given context,  the people in charge of determining its applicability (e.g., judges) rely on the same sorts of deliberations that first generated the norm under question, the deliberations that the norm was supposed to bypass in the first place.  Let’s assume that the norm’s legitimacy is not under question and that it has purchase. This would mean that the norm makes no practical difference in terms of determining its applicability, since this determination would rely on the very things the norm is intended to supersede.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, in some cases, purchase and efficacy do come apart. There is, of course, the question of whether purchase and efficacy are &lt;em&gt;individually necessary conditions and jointly sufficient&lt;/em&gt; for being a norm. So, for example, if a norm is efficacious but does not have purchase, is it in fact a norm or just &lt;em&gt;passing&lt;/em&gt; as a norm? Although things get more complicated when looking at specific types of norms (e.g., legal norms), I think it is safe to say that for norms writ-large, purchase and efficacy are common characteristics that bolster the &lt;em&gt;normness&lt;/em&gt; of norms, especially when they are both fulfilled. Given my focus in this piece, we can set aside the question of their necessity and/or sufficiency.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-fetishism-of-norms&#34;&gt;The fetishism of norms&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because of their purchase and efficacy, there is a tendency to view norms as given.  If a particular norm has ‘buy-in’ &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; it bypasses a certain amount of deliberation, then the norm assumes the character of a settled fact.  The norm isn’t &lt;em&gt;merely&lt;/em&gt; an illusion that we can look past, however. efficacious norms that have purchase by definition make a practical difference and have a grip on the world. In this way, they are objective.  Try and tell the judge presiding over your case that law you broke is “&lt;em&gt;just made up&lt;/em&gt;”! Therefore, it is not taking a norm as objective, but &lt;em&gt;taking the norm as a given naturalized fact&lt;/em&gt; that constitutes the &lt;em&gt;fetishism&lt;/em&gt; of norms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When a norm is efficacious, but does not have purchase it can still pass as given. If a community has a legal norm against jaywalking that can &lt;em&gt;potentially&lt;/em&gt; be used to cut deliberation  about the status of jaywalking, but is nonetheless flaunted and unenforced, this does not imply that the norm is taken as &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; being a naturalized norm. Put differently, a lack of purchase is not necessarily dependent on understanding norms as the result of the mediation of contingent social relations.  An efficacious norm that lacks purchase, but is still fetishized, is simply a norm that one can flaunt, unless additional criteria are satisfied. On its own, flaunting a norm does not necessarily imply a challenge to the norm’s giveness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you feel a &lt;em&gt;guilty pleasure&lt;/em&gt; in flaunting a norm, jaywalking to save time, you are both confirming the norm’s lack of purchase &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; its existence as a given, yet relatively unobtrusive, natural fact.   The fact of a norm’s giveness allows us the enjoyment of breaking it.  If a norm lacks purchase &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; is recognized as mediated and contingent, then the enjoyment of flaunting it flirts with outright delusion, which isn&amp;rsquo;t to say it doesn&amp;rsquo;t frequently happen. However, flaunting norms &lt;em&gt;can&lt;/em&gt; also, when additional conditions are met, indirectly challenge their giveness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;flaunting-norms&#34;&gt;Flaunting norms&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s start with the relatively unobjectionable premise that in his role as US President, Trump is doing harm. [2]  Aside from this, it seems that Trump is often under attack for flaunting norms, be it dinner etiquette or  legal norms. [3]  When Trump flaunts a norm, the norm is both &lt;em&gt;reaffirmed&lt;/em&gt; as a norm  and, at the very same time, its status as a norm is &lt;em&gt;questioned&lt;/em&gt;. [4]  On the one hand, in  critiquing Trump’s norm flaunting, the media is &lt;em&gt;reaffirming&lt;/em&gt; the norm as a legitimate norm.  On the other hand, Trump’s supporters are &lt;em&gt;also&lt;/em&gt; reaffirming the norm by enjoying his flaunting of it.  If the norm were not a norm, then there would be nothing remarkable or worth celebrating about Trump’s flaunting of it. For his supporters, the flaunted norm is an &lt;em&gt;illegitimate&lt;/em&gt; norm, but a norm nonetheless.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the bipolar act of reaffirming of a norm in the face of Trump flaunting it, the purchase of the norm is undermined. Its efficacy can also be revealed to be on shaky ground, for better or worse.  In some instances, reaffirming a norm involves deliberation over why a norm, if it lacks purchase, can still be rightfully called a “norm.” By this act of deliberation, the norm’s efficacy is dulled, if only temporarily. If we are deliberating over why a given norm is a norm, then the norm is not doing the work of an efficacious norm, which is to bypass such deliberation in the first place. While I do not think that such deliberation counts as &lt;em&gt;critique&lt;/em&gt; (in the sense used &lt;a href=&#34;https://valuethingfootnotes.wordpress.com/2020/10/25/there-is-a-thing-in-a-place/&#34;&gt;in a previous post&lt;/a&gt;), it can superficially reveal the ungiveness of the norm at issue and open the door for &lt;em&gt;actual critique&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is important to note two things about the context of Trump’s norm flaunting:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Although Trump flaunts some norms, he  follows and pays deference to many. As Corey Robin notes in this recent &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nybooks.com/daily/2020/10/21/the-gonzo-constitutionalism-of-the-american-right/&#34;&gt;piece&lt;/a&gt;, Trump and the Republicans  derive the majority of their “minority rule” power from the electoral college, the senate, and the courts (both supreme and lower courts).  So,  saying that Trump is anti-norm is simply wrong. There would be no presidential power for him to flaunt norms with if there were no norms whatsoever.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Trump’s political opponents and the media that decry his norm flaunting do not &lt;em&gt;necessarily&lt;/em&gt; disapprove of the action achieved in the breaking of a given norm, but rather show disdain that the norm that is supposed to precede the given action is disregarded.  Some of Democratic Primary Presidential candidates’ &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.npr.org/2020/01/06/794044686/democratic-presidential-candidates-criticize-trump-for-ordering-soleimani-strike&#34;&gt;responses&lt;/a&gt;  to Trump’s assassination of Qasem Soleimani are an interesting example of this.  The point is that, in such cases, the flaunting of a norm that achieves an acceptable result deflates the efficacy of  the norm.  If Trump can achieve results identical to those achieved following a norm, what good is the norm? By raising this question, Trump’s breaking of norms also erodes the &lt;em&gt;alibi&lt;/em&gt; that  norms usually provide.  Even when the norm is beyond absurd, it provides cover for both Republicans and Democrats. When the US Justice Department under Obama applied a “&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.washingtonpost.com/blogs/post-partisan/wp/2013/02/05/justice-department-chilling-drone-white-paper/&#34;&gt;broader concept of imminence&lt;/a&gt;” that flew in the face of any reasonable conception of the term in order to justify drone strikes (i.e., murder), it was doing so in order to ensure that their actions followed a norm––even if only &lt;em&gt;post facto&lt;/em&gt;.  While, in this instance, there was press scrutiny of the looseness and/or fraudulent manner in which the normness of  the given actions was achieved, there were no significant consequences for the actors involved. The norms may be flawed––even made up by the actors involved––but, even so, they are &lt;em&gt;norms&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://value-thing.github.io/images/if-the-rule.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;the rule you followed&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;&lt;i&gt;&amp;ldquo;If the rule you followed brought you to this, of what use was the rule?&amp;quot;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;normative-speculation&#34;&gt;Normative speculation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Knowing the role of purchase and efficacy in establishing normness implies that the ‘cash value’ of norms is only &lt;em&gt;validated&lt;/em&gt; when a norm is efficaciously put to the test. Prior to being tested, norms hold speculative value. While we can refer back to prior instances of a norm withstanding a test or a tests that led to a norm being put in practice in the first place (e.g., legal precedent),  this does not guarantee that the norm will continue to hold indefinitely.  Cashing out the speculative value of norms requires marshalling the right resources.  These resources include, but are not limited to, other norms (e.g., the norm to follow precedent), coercion, coordination, efficiency,  repetition, formalization, etc… While supporting one’s normative gamble with such resources can &lt;em&gt;help&lt;/em&gt; ensure that a norm will hold under a given test, it cannot guarantee it. The value of a norm can only be established through testing, so norms are conditioned by speculation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The flip side of validating the value of norms is that when one flaunts a norm, one is betting on the norm having little  value (e.g., lack of purchase and/or efficacy). Flaunting a norm is therefore as speculative as counting on a norm working and often relies on the same resources to minimize the risk involved in breaking a norm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Obviously, by flaunting norms Trump isn’t  doing anything good in itself. Like I said, he undeniably is causing harm, regardless of his norm infractions. He is nevertheless creating an opening for potentially understanding how norms work, that they rely on both purchase and efficacy in order to be norms and that these characteristics are not given.  In more general terms, norms are shown to be things that we generally do not explicitly deliberate in applying them if we consider them to be efficacious as norms.  Yet ,while they are not necessarily deliberated in their application, they nevertheless hinge on speculation and the management of the risk associated with it.  The norm needs to be continuously &lt;em&gt;reaffirmed&lt;/em&gt; by amassing the correct resources.  What counts as correct is not formally pre-determined, but contingent on context, including the social relations that ultimately affirm/deny the normness of a norm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When we &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt; explicitly deliberate norms,  their status as norms is challenged.  When Trump flaunts a norm, despite the reaffirming of the norm, he unintentionally raises the questions, “Why are our norms the way they are? Why did the norm flaunter bet on being able to flaunt the given norm? “ In the case of Trump, this has lead to an endless litany of nonsense and vitriol, but there’s also a way in which this question may potentially generate the conditions for the possibility of identifying the fetishism of norms, the fact that such norms are not naturalized givens, but arise out of social relations , which, in turn, influence those very social relations.   Identifying how norms arise and are sustained is the starting point for the possibility of critiquing their relation to our current state of affairs, capitalism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As always, there is the risk that the question simply results in further misapprehension. This seems to be the way things have generally gone with regard to Trump specifically.  Beyond this, the identification of fetishism does not mean that norms simply &lt;em&gt;up and vanish&lt;/em&gt;. They are objective facts of the social world. Knowing how a car works doesn’t mean that you can do anything you want with it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;Footnotes&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[1] In line with Adorno, taking a norm as a given is taking something that is ‘subject’ and treating it as an ‘object’. In this sense, fetishized norms are the &lt;em&gt;objectivization of the subject&lt;/em&gt;. I discuss this and giveness at greater length &lt;a href=&#34;https://valuethingfootnotes.wordpress.com/2020/10/25/there-is-a-thing-in-a-place/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.  It should also be noted that I am playing fast and loose with the concept of fetishism. While I think that there is a strong case to be made concerning the specificity of norm fetishism under capitalism, I will not be making that case here.  Evgeny Pashukanis tackles this type of fetishism in the context of law and capitalism in his 1924 book, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.marxists.org/archive/pashukanis/1924/law/index.htm&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The General Theory of Law &amp;amp; Marxism&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[2]  The question of whether “Trump is worst President ever,” whether “Trump is doing more harm than Presidents X, Y, and Z,” or whether “Any one  can fulfill the role of President &lt;em&gt;without&lt;/em&gt; causing harm” is irrelevant in the given context. The only thing that is relevant is that Trump is causing harm in fulfilling his role and that he flaunts and/or is perceived to flaunt norms.  I am leaving harm undefined, since the specific kinds of harms Trump is causing are unimportant to the argument.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[3] The intense focus on Trump’s flaunting of norms is evidenced by the almost obsessive nature that the liberal press documents his infractions, whether it be focused on &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.washingtonpost.com/graphics/2020/outlook/siskind-list-trump-norms/&#34;&gt;norms-writ-large&lt;/a&gt; or specific norms, such as &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.vox.com/2020/10/23/21530079/cnn-debate-fact-check-trump-biden&#34;&gt;making false claims&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[4] The question of whether Trump intentionally flaunts norms is unimportant for our purposes.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>