<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Marx on Value Thing</title>
    <link>https://value-thing.github.io/tags/marx/</link>
    <description>Value Thing (Marx)</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 30 Oct 2020 00:00:00 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
    <atom:link href="https://value-thing.github.io/tags/marx/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Quick thoughts on voting</title>
      <link>https://value-thing.github.io/post/quickthoughtsonvoting/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Oct 2020 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://value-thing.github.io/post/quickthoughtsonvoting/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I do not presume to have a knockdown argument &lt;em&gt;for or against&lt;/em&gt; voting in national elections. Approaching voting as an act that can be evaluated in isolation, seems to raise more questions than it resolves. For example, by looking at voting alone, it becomes difficult to confirm or deny that &lt;em&gt;Your Vote Is Important&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;This Election Is (The Most) Important&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;!-- more --&gt; On the one hand, in tight races a single vote seems to be become undeniably important, in some sense. On the other, in the bigger picture a vote is simply one among many. If a single vote is deciding the election how do we pick which one is the deciding vote? If a party loses by a single vote and A and B were intending to vote for the losing party, but didn’t, is A or is B responsible for the party losing? Are they both? Or maybe it is the party itself that is responsible, since it was unable to create the motivation required for A or B to vote in the first place.  &lt;em&gt;These are the questions that I want to avoid.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;recipes-for-an-individual-act&#34;&gt;Recipes for an individual act&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Relatively depoliticized campaigns to &lt;em&gt;Get Out The Vote&lt;/em&gt; and more politicized “movements” that spend significant resources on getting their members to vote tend to downplay or misapprehend what a vote is. Each of these approaches to voting can be seen, at least in part, as making up the &lt;em&gt;recipe&lt;/em&gt; that leads a given individual to vote––either to vote &lt;em&gt;in general&lt;/em&gt; or to vote for a specific party/candidate.  However, once an individual gets to the ballot box and votes, this recipe is largely abstracted from the vote itself.   Whatever social, economic, ideological, and/or political motivations go into the vote recipe, in the &lt;em&gt;act of voting&lt;/em&gt; these are boiled down to a singularly political act––more of an abstract ode to ‘citizenship’ than the expression of a struggle or ‘movement’.  Whatever perspective goes into casting a vote, it is the perspective of the bodies that administer the terrain on which elections play out that matters. This perspective will not and &lt;em&gt;cannot&lt;/em&gt; directly apprehend a single vote as anything but an individual act.  Voting, under these circumstances, becomes analogous to accepting the terms for an unfair fight in which the voter is at a disadvantage. This is the form that voting takes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-vampire-state&#34;&gt;The vampire state&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;CEOs, hedge fund managers, and landlords don’t need to rely solely on votes to get their objectives achieved. This would be ineffective and likely disastrous for capital accumulation.  Regardless of whether they know it &lt;em&gt;as such&lt;/em&gt;, a vote is transaction in which concrete economic/social/ideological/political concerns are translated into abstract political concerns. The exchange rate on such a transaction does not favour &lt;em&gt;any&lt;/em&gt; voter.  However, the vote exchange rate in a capitalist state is especially unfavourable to those outside of the bourgeoisie. Without delving into how one conceives of the state (e.g., autonomous, epiphenomenal, instrumental, etc…), a capitalist state must, well…somehow sustain capitalism. Thus, when one’s voting recipe is exchanged for a vote, becoming an individualized and abstract political act, it is translated into the terms of the capitalist state.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While a vote may be aggregated with others as a representation of particular ‘interests’––extrapolating from exit poll data, for example–– each of these interests is nevertheless abstracted from its original concrete and contextualized manifestations.  These &lt;em&gt;interest positions&lt;/em&gt; are mapped onto the existing economic/social/legal/ideological/political terrain of the state. Needless to say, anything like class struggle largely disappears and is replaced with the objective &lt;em&gt;appearance&lt;/em&gt; of an electorate with competing interest positions that must be realigned and ideally harmonized––this necessarily sometimes involves a degree of compromise and change––with the existing terrain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;not-nothing&#34;&gt;Not nothing&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It would be hyperbolic to say the above amounts to a &lt;em&gt;refutation of voting&lt;/em&gt;. Firstly, as I said, I think the question of voting &lt;em&gt;as such&lt;/em&gt; doesn’t say much about anything. It is abstract question about an act of abstraction. Therefore, my interest does not lie with a rejection of voting in itself. Secondly, notwithstanding the above, the &lt;em&gt;abstraction of voting&lt;/em&gt; takes place in a real context.  The potential gains of participating in the abstraction are real and may, in significant ways, ameliorate the lives of voters. Such gains cannot be simply discounted on the basis that they are the result of adopting the terms of an unfair fight.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That said––and this is an obvious point to most––if a vote is to be cast, it should be cast with knowledge of the abstraction that takes place.  While this knowledge doesn’t amount to much on its own, it can &lt;em&gt;and does&lt;/em&gt; lead struggles to look beyond &lt;em&gt;the struggle to vote&lt;/em&gt;.  This type of political education may need to reassess the relation and tension between proximate, often critical if not necessary, material gains and the challenges required to achieve the overcoming of the present––flexible–– &lt;em&gt;form&lt;/em&gt; of the capitalist state.  Through such analysis it may be possible to identify the manner in which material gains coincide with the establishment of conditions more favourable to class struggle. However, achieving  the benefits of the welfare state &lt;em&gt;without fragmenting the working class to the overall benefit of capital accumulation&lt;/em&gt; is a difficult needle to thread, one that has been debated for decades.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This implies that political education to be political &lt;em&gt;cannot&lt;/em&gt; be simply about how to organize the masses to vote one way or another.  It must rather tackle the question of how to avoid the exchange of social + economic +political concerns for purely political ones framed by the existing state, how to set the terms so that the fight is at least &lt;em&gt;less unfair&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Norms fetishism</title>
      <link>https://value-thing.github.io/post/normsfetishism/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 Oct 2020 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://value-thing.github.io/post/normsfetishism/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I want to focus on two aspects of norms writ-large (e.g., legal norms, social norms, etc…) in order to tease out some implications about the fetishism of norms (i.e.,  objective norms that appear as naturalized entities):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A norm’s &lt;em&gt;purchase&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A norm’s &lt;em&gt;efficacy&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although I think the question of whether they are necessary and/or sufficient conditions being a norm is interesting, the focus of this post does not hinge on this. Regardless of their status as necessary and/or sufficient conditions, I think these concepts are useful for assessing how norms &lt;em&gt;function&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- more --&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;purchase-and-efficacy&#34;&gt;Purchase and efficacy&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Purchase&lt;/strong&gt; refers to a norm’s &lt;em&gt;grip&lt;/em&gt; within the context that it is intended to be applied. This grip can be the result of a many number of things, often in combination, such as community interest and/or some form of enforcement.  Purchase amounts to a norm’s recognition as a norm and it comes in degrees.  If a norm has both legal enforcement and community recognition (positive or negative) it has a &lt;em&gt;stronger&lt;/em&gt;  grip than if the norm was simply enforced.  While some legal norms are enforceable, often times it seems as if community recognition of  these norms &lt;em&gt;as norms&lt;/em&gt; is generally sufficient to guarantee the grip of norms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;efficacy&lt;/strong&gt; refers to the fact that a norm makes a practical difference. So, if the norm did not exist, there would be no practical difference within a given context. What I mean by “practical difference” requires some unpacking.  To start, we can say that if a norm makes a practical difference, it allows us to &lt;em&gt;do something&lt;/em&gt; that would otherwise not be possible.  Some theorists argue that norms &lt;em&gt;allow us&lt;/em&gt; to bypass lengthy deliberation on relatively “settled” questions. In his book &lt;em&gt;Legality&lt;/em&gt; (2011), Scott Shapiro states that&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unless the community has a way of reducing the costs and risks of
planning, resolving these moral problems will be, at best, expensive and,
at worst, impossible. On the Planning Theory, the fundamental aim of
the law is to meet this moral demand in an efficient manner. By providing
a highly nimble and durable method of social planning, the law enables
communities to solve the numerous and serious problems that
would otherwise be too costly or risky to resolve. (213)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While norms are a broader category than law––not to mention that, strictly speaking, Shapiro views laws as “plans”––this characterization can be &lt;em&gt;mutatis mutandis&lt;/em&gt; applied to norms writ-large. This is the aspect of efficacy that I will focus on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;coming-apart&#34;&gt;Coming apart&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At first glance, purchase and efficacy seem to go hand-in-hand. If a norm has a &lt;em&gt;grip&lt;/em&gt;, then it must also &lt;em&gt;do something&lt;/em&gt;, right? Not necessarily.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Imagine that you are living in a community where drinking alcohol in a public park without a special permit (e.g., an event permit) is illegal.  Let’s say that when the local softball league uses the public park for their tournaments, the players drink alcohol without a permit. While they take measures to disguise their drinks, it is common knowledge––even in law-enforcement––that the players are, in fact, drinking alcohol &lt;em&gt;illegally&lt;/em&gt;.  Despite this, the rule is not enforced and generally, aside from the occasional complaint, the community is fine with it. In this case, the norm is &lt;em&gt;efficacious&lt;/em&gt; in the sense that norm leaves no question that the players are doing something illegal (i.e., going against a legal norm). Although one may debate the legitimacy of the norm, no one needs to deliberate whether or not these actions are, in fact, illegal.  However, in this case, &lt;em&gt;the norm seems to lack purchase&lt;/em&gt;: the community and law enforcement are more-or-less fine with disregarding the norm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A norm with purchase, but no efficacy is more difficult, but not impossible, to conceive. Imagine, as some do, that in making decisions about the applicability of a norm in a given context,  the people in charge of determining its applicability (e.g., judges) rely on the same sorts of deliberations that first generated the norm under question, the deliberations that the norm was supposed to bypass in the first place.  Let’s assume that the norm’s legitimacy is not under question and that it has purchase. This would mean that the norm makes no practical difference in terms of determining its applicability, since this determination would rely on the very things the norm is intended to supersede.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, in some cases, purchase and efficacy &lt;em&gt;do come apart&lt;/em&gt;. There is, of course, the question of whether purchase and efficacy are &lt;em&gt;individually necessary conditions and jointly sufficient&lt;/em&gt; of being a norm. So, for example, if a norm is efficacious but does not have purchase, is it in fact a norm or just &lt;em&gt;passing&lt;/em&gt; as a norm? Although things get more complicated when looking at specific types of norms (e.g., legal norms), I think it is safe to say that for norm writ-large, purchase and efficacy are &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; necessary. Rather, they are common characteristics that bolster the &lt;em&gt;normness&lt;/em&gt; of norms when they are both fulfilled.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-fetishism-of-norms&#34;&gt;The fetishism of norms&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because of their purchase and efficacy, there is a tendency to view norms as given.  If a particular norm has ‘buy-in’ &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; it bypasses a certain amount of deliberation, then the norm assumes the character of a settled fact.  The norm isn’t &lt;em&gt;merely&lt;/em&gt; an illusion that we can look past, however. efficacious norms that have purchase by definition make a practical difference and have a grip on the world. In this way, they are objective.  Try and tell the judge presiding over your case that law you broke is “&lt;em&gt;just made up&lt;/em&gt;”! Therefore, it is not taking a norm as objective, but &lt;em&gt;taking the norm as a Given naturalized fact&lt;/em&gt; that constitutes the &lt;em&gt;fetishism&lt;/em&gt; of norms. [1]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When a norm is efficacious, but does not have purchase it can still &lt;em&gt;pass&lt;/em&gt; as Given. If a community has a legal norm against jaywalking that can &lt;em&gt;potentially&lt;/em&gt; be used to cut deliberation  about the status of jaywalking, but is nonetheless flaunted and unenforced, this does not imply that the norm is taken as &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; being a naturalized norm. Put differently, a lack of purchase is not necessarily dependent on understanding norms as the result of the mediation of contingent social relations.  An efficacious norm that lacks purchase, but is still fetishized, is simply a norm that one can flaunt, unless additional criteria are satisfied. On its own, flaunting a norm does not necessarily imply a challenge to the norm’s giveness. When you feel a &lt;em&gt;guilty pleasure&lt;/em&gt; in flaunting a norm, jaywalking to save time, you are both confirming the norm’s lack of purchase &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; its existence as a given, yet relatively unobtrusive, natural fact.   The fact of a norm’s giveness allows us the enjoyment of breaking it.  If a norm lack’s purchase &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; is recognized as mediated and contingent, then the enjoyment of flaunting it flirts with outright delusion. However, flaunting norms &lt;em&gt;can&lt;/em&gt; also, when additional conditions are met, indirectly challenge their giveness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;reaffirming-and-questioning-norms-by-flaunting-them&#34;&gt;Reaffirming and questioning norms by flaunting them&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s start with the relatively unobjectionable premise that in his role as US President, Trump is doing harm. [2]  Aside from this and maybe partial relation to it, it seems that Trump is often under attack for flaunting norms, be it dinner etiquette or  legal norms. [3]  When Trump flaunts a norm, the norm is both &lt;em&gt;reaffirmed&lt;/em&gt; as a norm  and, at the very same time, its status as a norm is &lt;em&gt;questioned&lt;/em&gt;.  The question of whether Trump intentionally flaunts norms is unimportant for our purposes.  On the one hand, in  critiquing Trump’s norm flaunting,  his opponents are  &lt;em&gt;reaffirming&lt;/em&gt; the norm as a legitimate norm.  On the other hand, Trump’s supporters are &lt;em&gt;also&lt;/em&gt; reaffirming the norm by enjoying his flaunting of it.  If the norm were not a norm, then there would be nothing remarkable or worth celebrating about Trump’s flaunting of it. For his supporters, the flaunted norm is an &lt;em&gt;illegitimate&lt;/em&gt; norm, but a norm nonetheless.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the bipolar act of reaffirming of a norm in the face of Trump flaunting it, the purchase of the norm is undermined. However, its efficacy can also be revealed to be on shaky ground, for better or worse.  In some instances, reaffirming a norm involves deliberation over why a norm, if it lacks purchase, can still rightfully called a “norm.” By this act of deliberation, the norm’s efficacy is dulled, if only temporarily. If we are deliberating over why a given norm is a norm, then the norm is not doing what a norm does in order to be efficacious, which is to bypass such deliberation in the first place. While I do not think that such deliberation counts as &lt;em&gt;critique&lt;/em&gt; (in the sense used &lt;a href=&#34;https://valuethingfootnotes.wordpress.com/2020/10/25/there-is-a-thing-in-a-place/&#34;&gt;in a previous post&lt;/a&gt;, it can superficially reveal the ungiveness of the norm at issue and open the door for &lt;em&gt;actual critique&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;**ADDED PARAGRAPH&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is important to note two things about the context of Trump’s norm flaunting:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Although Trump flaunts some norms, he  follows and pays deference to many.  As Corey Robin notes in this recent &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nybooks.com/daily/2020/10/21/the-gonzo-constitutionalism-of-the-american-right/&#34;&gt;piece&lt;/a&gt; , Trump and the Republicans  derive the majority of their “minority rule” power from the electoral college, the senate, and the courts (both supreme and lower courts).  So,  saying that Trump is anti-norm is simply wrong. There would be no presidential power for him to flaunt norms with if there were no norms whatsoever. He is only flaunts some norms.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Trump’s political opponents and the media that decry his norm flaunting do not &lt;em&gt;necessarily&lt;/em&gt; disapprove of the action achieved in the breaking of a given norm, but rather show disdain that the norm that is supposed to precede the given action is disregarded.  Some of Democratic Primary Presidential candidates’ [responses] (&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.npr.org/2020/01/06/794044686/democratic-presidential-candidates-criticize-trump-for-ordering-soleimani-strike&#34;&gt;https://www.npr.org/2020/01/06/794044686/democratic-presidential-candidates-criticize-trump-for-ordering-soleimani-strike&lt;/a&gt;)  to Trump’s assassination of Qasem Soleimani are an interesting example of this.  The point is that, in such cases, the flaunting of a norm that achieves an acceptable result deflates the efficacy of  the norm.  If Trump can achieve results identical to those achieved following a norm, what good is the norm? By raising this question, Trump’s breaking of norms also erodes the &lt;em&gt;alibi&lt;/em&gt; that  norms usually provide.  Even when the norm is beyond absurd, it provides cover for both Republicans and Democrats. When the US Justice Department under Obama applied a “[broader concept of imminence] (&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.washingtonpost.com/blogs/post-partisan/wp/2013/02/05/justice-department-chilling-drone-white-paper/&#34;&gt;https://www.washingtonpost.com/blogs/post-partisan/wp/2013/02/05/justice-department-chilling-drone-white-paper/&lt;/a&gt;)” that flew in the face of any reasonable conception of the term in order to justify drone strikes (i.e., murder), it was doing so in order to ensure that their actions followed a norm––even if only&lt;em&gt;post facto&lt;/em&gt;.  While, in this instance, there was press scrutiny of the looseness and/or fraudulent manner in which the normness of  the given actions was achieved, there were no significant consequences for the actors involved. The norms may be flawed––even made up by the actors involved––but they are norms nonetheless.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;normative-speculation&#34;&gt;Normative speculation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Knowing the role of purchase and efficacy in establishing normness implies that the ‘cash value’ of norms is only &lt;em&gt;validated&lt;/em&gt; when a norm is efficaciously put to the test. Prior to being tested, norms hold speculative value. While we can refer back to prior instances of a norm withstanding a test or a tests that led to a norm being put in practice in the first place (e.g., legal precedent),  this does not guarantee that the norm will continue to hold indefinitely.  Cashing out the speculative value of norms requires marshalling the right resources.  These resources include, but are not limited to, other norms (e.g., the norm to follow precedent), coercive force, financial resources, coordination, efficiency,  repetition, formalization, etc… While supporting one’s normative gamble with such resources can &lt;em&gt;help&lt;/em&gt; ensure that a norm will hold under a given test, it cannot guarantee it. The value of a norm can only be established through testing, so norms are conditioned by speculativeness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The flip side of validating a norms is that when one flaunts a norm, one is betting on the norm having little  value (e.g., lack of purchase and/or efficacy). Flaunting a norm is therefore as speculative as counting on a norm working and often relies on the same resources  to minimize the risk involved in breaking a norm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Obviously, by flaunting norms Trump isn’t  doing anything good in itself. Like I said, he undeniably is causing harm, regardless of his norm infractions.  He is nevertheless creating an opening for potentially understanding how norms work, that they rely on both purchase and efficacy in order to be norms and that these characteristics are not given.  In more general terms, norms are shown to be things that we generally do not explicitly deliberate in applying them if we consider them to be efficacious as norms.  Yet ,while they are not necessarily deliberated in their application, they nevertheless hinge on speculation and the management of the risk associated with it.  The norm needs to be continuously &lt;em&gt;reaffirmed&lt;/em&gt; by amassing the correct resources.  What counts as correct is not formally pre-determined, but contingent on context, including the social relations that ultimately affirm/deny the normness of a norm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When we &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt; explicitly deliberate norms,  their status as norms is challenged.  When Trump flaunts a norm, despite the reaffirming of the norm, he unintentionally raises the questions, “Why are our norms the way they are? Why did the norm flaunter bet on being able to flaunt the given norm? “ In the case of Trump, this has lead to an endless litany of nonsense and vitriol, but there’s also a way in which this question may potentially generate the conditions for the possibility of identifying the fetishism of norms, the fact that such norms are not naturalized givens, but arise out of social relations , which, in turn, influence those very social relations.   Identifying how norms arise and are sustained is the starting point for the possibility of critique their relation to our current state of affairs, capitalism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As always, there is the risk that the question simply results in further misapprehension. This seems to be the way things have generally gone with regard to Trump specifically.  Beyond this, the identification of fetishism does not mean that norms simply &lt;em&gt;up and vanish&lt;/em&gt;. They are objective facts of the social world. Knowing how a car works doesn’t mean that you can do anything you want with it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;Footnotes&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[1]: In line with Adorno, taking a norm as a given is taking something that is ‘subject’ and treating it as an ‘object’. In this sense, fetishized norms are the &lt;em&gt;objectivization of the subject&lt;/em&gt;. I discuss this and giveness at greater length &lt;a href=&#34;https://valuethingfootnotes.wordpress.com/2020/10/25/there-is-a-thing-in-a-place/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.  It should also be noted that I am playing fast and loose with the concept of fetishism. While I think that there is a strong case to be made concerning the specificity of norm fetishism under capitalism, I will not be making that case here.  Evgeny Pashukanis tackles this type of fetishism in the legal context in his 1924 book, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.marxists.org/archive/pashukanis/1924/law/index.htm&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The General Theory of Law &amp;amp; Marxism&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[2]  The question of whether “Trump is worst President ever,” whether “Trump is doing more harm than Presidents X, Y, and Z,” or whether “Any one  can, under the given circumstances (i.e., capitalism), fulfill the role of President &lt;em&gt;without&lt;/em&gt; causing harm” is irrelevant in the given context. The only thing that is relevant is that Trump is causing harm in fulfilling his role and that he flaunts and/or is perceived to flaunt norms.  I am leaving harm undefined, since the specific kinds of harms Trump is causing are unimportant to the argument.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[3] The intense focus on Trump’s flaunting of norms is evidenced by the almost obsessive nature that the liberal press documents his infractions, whether it be focused on &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.washingtonpost.com/graphics/2020/outlook/siskind-list-trump-norms/&#34;&gt;norms-writ-large&lt;/a&gt; or specific norms, such as &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.vox.com/2020/10/23/21530079/cnn-debate-fact-check-trump-biden&#34;&gt;making false claims&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What I am talking about when I avoid talking about &#39;Marxism as a science&#39;, but still talk about Marxism as being scientific</title>
      <link>https://value-thing.github.io/post/scientificmarxism/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Oct 2020 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://value-thing.github.io/post/scientificmarxism/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-basic-questions&#34;&gt;The basic questions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When discussions about “Marxism as a science”(MS) pop up, they often involve equivocations between, on the one hand, the meaning of “science” and, on the other, the meaning of “Marxism.” While the latter equivocation is part and parcel of the ‘joys’ of being a Marxist, the former one &lt;em&gt;seems&lt;/em&gt; specific to the issue of MS and consequently more primary.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- more --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some people take Marxism to be a science in the sense that it  operates like a natural science and targets similar phenomena. Sometimes, this view is ostensibly refined by specifying that Marxism operates like a “social science.”  Unfortunately, this latter move simply pushes back the question of “What is science and how is Marxism like it?” by an extra step. The question then becomes two questions “What is social science and how is Marxism like it?” and “What is science and how is social science like it?”  While this seems like a potentially useful endeavour in certain contexts, for the purposes of identifying MS , it merely adds an assumption that needs to be investigated prior to the original question. Put differently, we should be able to figure out how Marxism is like a science without also knowing how social science is like science.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since the &lt;em&gt;rejection&lt;/em&gt; of MS hinges on the identification of criteria for &lt;em&gt;what counts as science&lt;/em&gt;, it must also wrestle with the question of “What is science and how is Marxism like it?”  This is means that a productive debate about whether Marxism is a science would first have to settle the more basic question “&lt;em&gt;What is science?&lt;/em&gt;”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Answering this question will also help ensure that we’re not speaking at cross-purposes in a debate over the status of MS. For example, let’s assume that A argues that ‘science = falsifiable empirical research’ and B argues that ‘science = any systematized and self-correcting body of knowledge.’ Even if A and B both agree (or disagree) with the proposition that “Marxism is a science,” there is no  &lt;em&gt;substantive&lt;/em&gt; agreement between the two. The only agreement generated in this case is that &lt;em&gt;according to their respective stipulations of science, A and B do (or do not) view Marxism as a science&lt;/em&gt;.  A and B’s stipulations may not only be different, but in conflict––once again raising the question, “&lt;em&gt;What is science&lt;/em&gt;?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;why-i-will-not-tell-you-what-science-is&#34;&gt;Why I will not tell you what science is&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don’t have the time, the expertise, nor the will to tackle the question of what it is that makes a given practice &amp;ldquo;science,&amp;rdquo; but it is a worthwhile one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moreover,  I don’t think the answer to this question can be cashed out on its own for significant gains, aside from rhetorical ones––which is not nothing, but also not my concern &lt;em&gt;at this very moment&lt;/em&gt;.  Once we have an answer to the question “What is science?” we still have to figure out the original question, “Is Marxism a science?”, which itself hinges on knowing what Marxism is.  My view is that once we figure out what is meant by ‘Marxism’, specifically what types of things ‘Marxism’ allows one to do, the question of whether it is a science becomes largely a terminological and rhetorical issue.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;why-i-will-not-tell-you-what-marxism-is&#34;&gt;Why I will not tell you what Marxism is&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Originally, I made the case that the question “What is science?” is more basic than “What is Marxism?”, but now I am arguing that the former question is a bit of a sideshow, given that the question “Is Marxism a science?” is overshadowed by the pragmatic implications of something qualifying as ‘Marxism’  (i.e., what Marxism allows you to do).  Now, to confuse things further, to bring us back to the beginning, &lt;em&gt;I will not even bother with telling you what Marxism is.&lt;/em&gt; While I think  there is something identifiably Marxist in all honest expressions of Marxism, I’m almost positive that this common property may simply be the fact that Marxist authors refer to Marx or other Marxists in a loosely, but not uniformly or even overwhelmingly, positive fashion (e.g., Analytical Marxism vs. Western Marxism).  This commonality is a mere triviality that generates other trivialities and, occasionally, these are put forward as insightful : “There isn’t &lt;em&gt;a&lt;/em&gt; Marxism, there are &lt;em&gt;Marxisms&lt;/em&gt;!” and “Marxists  seem to only spend their time arguing with one another!” Moving on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;doing-things-with-marxism&#34;&gt;Doing things with ‘Marxism’&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are instances where the connection between Marxism and science does seem salient, where &lt;em&gt;Marxism is behaving like a science, in the sense that Marxism is fulfilling the criteria that have been stipulated for what counts as science&lt;/em&gt;.  In his book, &lt;em&gt;Continuity and Rupture&lt;/em&gt; (2016), J. Moufawad-Paul outlines how Marxism-Leninism-Maoism, under his conception of MLM and science, &lt;em&gt;does just this&lt;/em&gt;.  This is no trivial accomplishment.  Although I find his argument compelling, I will not delve into the details, given that this would bring us back to the &lt;em&gt;basic questions&lt;/em&gt; that I am intent on avoiding. Regardless of his argument’s merits, what Moufawad-Paul does in his book is to show how a particular conception of Marxism &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; science, allows one to &lt;em&gt;do certain things&lt;/em&gt;, including practical things in the world.  Moufawad-Paul is not merely mulling over the basic questions––providing nuance and specificity to the relevant definitions––but  &lt;em&gt;showing&lt;/em&gt; how the conceptions he presents make a practical difference. While Moufawad-Paul’s argument for MLM is constructed as hinging on it being a &lt;em&gt;science&lt;/em&gt; of revolution, in my view the tight link between science and Marxism that he argues for is perhaps better seen as a by-product of the practices and inferences that his conception generates.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If a conception does what it says it does, which is to make a practical difference, then what difference does it make to label this conception “a science”?  It largely seems to be a compliment that we are paying to something because it does what it says it does. Questions of whether the connection between a particular conception of MS and the natural sciences is literal or metaphorical or whether MS is more akin to a social science are secondary to the question of what sorts of practices, inferences, and effects this conception affords. It seems to me that often times what we do when we say we are putting forward MS is opening ourselves to debating the &lt;em&gt;basic questions&lt;/em&gt;. Questions that are likely fruitful, but also secondary and highly contentious.  That said, maybe I am just succumbing  to the influence of the perennial &lt;em&gt;Show Don’t Tell&lt;/em&gt; mantra of writing.  And, if this is the case, I must also be partial to the &lt;em&gt;Do As I Say, Not As I Do&lt;/em&gt; school of thought.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;marxism-and-the-scientific-image&#34;&gt;Marxism and the scientific image&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having argued that MS is an issue of secondary importance, I also––perhaps paradoxically––believe that it is crucial for Marxism to be “scientific” in the Sellarsian sense of being a project that is  situated in the &lt;em&gt;scientific image&lt;/em&gt; rather than the &lt;em&gt;manifest image&lt;/em&gt;.  As sketched out in the previous post, the difference between the manifest image and the scientific image can be roughly glossed as the difference between normative and intentionally-oriented &lt;em&gt;evaluations&lt;/em&gt;, on the one hand, and non-normative and non-intentional &lt;em&gt;explanations&lt;/em&gt;, on the other. Although the scientific image emerges from the manifest image, neither image is reducible to the other. In fact, paradoxically, through its postulation of “imperceptible entities, and principles pertaining to them, to explain the behaviour of perceptible things” (e.g., natural selection, class struggle, etc…),  the scientific image can, in fact, explain how aspects of the manifest arose in the first place .&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In &lt;em&gt;explaining&lt;/em&gt; the real and effective &lt;em&gt;appearances&lt;/em&gt; of capitalism by identifying “imperceptible entities,” which include value, fetishism, and social relations (etc…), Marx’s approach to the critique of political economy seems to fall in the scientific image.  Other aspects are not so easy to square with this view. Even disregarding the potentially non-scientific image aspects of Marx, this &lt;em&gt;does not&lt;/em&gt; mean, even in the  Sellarsian idiom, that specific expressions of Marxism are “scientific” in the way most people intend when they appeal to MS.  Rather, Sellars was careful to note that the manifest image was not “pre-scientific”, but included what would be considered science. For him, what counts as &lt;em&gt;scientific&lt;/em&gt; in the sense of belonging to the scientific image is the prioritization of &lt;em&gt;explanations&lt;/em&gt;  that use non-normative and non-intentional concepts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, even if I am willing to say with confidence that Marxism is scientific ––albeit &lt;em&gt;in a Sellarsian sense&lt;/em&gt;––this does not entitle me, for now, to proclaim Marxism as a science (in the unspecified way most people mean).  I hope that this  view amounts to more than word games, that the distinction between “science” and “scientific image” is more than simply a matter of hedging my bets or having it both ways. So far,  using Sellars to read Marx has allowed me to approach Marx in immediately fruitful ways, but this could obviously change once I do more work and actually put some of these ideas to the test.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;{{ partial &amp;ldquo;staticman.html&amp;rdquo; . }}&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>On the very idea of critique</title>
      <link>https://value-thing.github.io/post/ontheveryideaofcritique/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 25 Oct 2020 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://value-thing.github.io/post/ontheveryideaofcritique/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;When I say something I use words, but the words do not necessarily &lt;em&gt;get at&lt;/em&gt; what I am trying to say. They are placeholders, frames, that are part of an attempt to connect my mind and the world for a given purpose. The world is obviously here and I am obviously &lt;em&gt;in it&lt;/em&gt; saying something &lt;em&gt;about it&lt;/em&gt;, but the words nonetheless do not fully capture the world. Otherwise, there would simply be no distinction between mind and world. Although the subject (mind) and the object (world) form a whole, they are distinct.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- more --&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;my-dog-is-in-the-backyard&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;My dog is in the backyard&amp;rdquo;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I say, &amp;ldquo;My dog is in the backyard,&amp;rdquo; I am shaping my own thoughts using concepts that are &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; my own creation, but are, despite this, used by me &lt;em&gt;creatively&lt;/em&gt;. I am inculcated from birth into a language that is not my own. I may create an entirely new language, but it will nevertheless have been influenced by the concepts that originally formed me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The use of the word &amp;lsquo;dog&amp;rsquo; instantiates the concept &amp;lsquo;Dog&amp;rsquo;, but this concept is vague and filled in contextually depending on the circumstances of its use. For example, by using the adjective &amp;ldquo;my&amp;rdquo; along with &amp;ldquo;dog,&amp;rdquo; I add additional determinations to the concept &amp;lsquo;Dog&amp;rsquo;. It is not just any dog, but &lt;em&gt;my&lt;/em&gt; dog. So, even if I didn&amp;rsquo;t know anything about the dog, I would know that the dog bears a particular relation to me. The word &amp;ldquo;the&amp;rdquo; in the context of &amp;ldquo;the backyard&amp;rdquo; indicates not just any backyard, but &lt;em&gt;the&lt;/em&gt; backyard where &lt;em&gt;my&lt;/em&gt; dog is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite this, the words that express concepts are imprecise on their own. The &lt;em&gt;pragmatics&lt;/em&gt; of language-use seem to be as crucial as their &lt;em&gt;semantics&lt;/em&gt;. What I am doing with the words and in what context is as important as the words themselves. Going further, when we appeal to dictionary definitions (i.e., lexical meanings), this is itself a pragmatic constraint on the semantics: &amp;ldquo;When I use this word I want you to consider its meaning as being tightly linked to this definition.&amp;rdquo; If lexical meaning are determined by use, then it seems that dictionary definitions and language-use are in a cyclical feedback relation. We codify linguistic behaviours and then these guide, but do not determine our future language use.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Donald Davidson makes a point of highlighting instances in which language use &lt;em&gt;goes wrong&lt;/em&gt; in order to clarify the fact that lexical meaning is only a part of what we draw from when we communicate. For example, let&amp;rsquo;s say I mistakenly utter, &amp;ldquo;My &lt;em&gt;drog&lt;/em&gt; is in the backyard,&amp;rdquo; with the intention of conveying that &amp;lsquo;my &lt;em&gt;dog&lt;/em&gt; is in the backyard&amp;rsquo;. Despite my mistake in uttering the word &amp;ldquo;dog,&amp;rdquo; there is nevertheless a likelihood, given the right circumstances (e.g., that my interlocutor knows the english language, knows what the word &amp;ldquo;dog&amp;rdquo; means, and knows that I have a dog), that my interlocutor will correctly interpret me as meaning &amp;lsquo;My &lt;em&gt;dog&lt;/em&gt; is in the backyard&amp;rsquo;. This implies that language use can diverge from the strict &lt;em&gt;form&lt;/em&gt; of terms without affecting meaning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If we can adjust for deviations in form to generate the intended meaning of an utterance, then perhaps there is a &lt;em&gt;relatively&lt;/em&gt; stable lexical meaning, after all. However, this possibility is challenged when we examine how words can be used in novel ways or metaphorically. For example, let&amp;rsquo;s say I live in an apartment block that does not have a backyard, but has a municipal park behind it. I simply refer to this park as my &amp;ldquo;backyard,&amp;rdquo; despite it not fulfilling the standard conditions of the lexical meaning of &amp;ldquo;backyard.&amp;rdquo; As long as the contextual circumstances lead an interpreter to infer that when I say &amp;ldquo;backyard&amp;rdquo; I am referring to the municipal park, then I have used this word to generate meaning without strictly following the lexical meaning of the term. A similar thing can occur if I use the term metaphorically, such as if I say, &amp;ldquo;The world is my backyard.&amp;rdquo; While I am partially relying on lexical meaning, the context in which the word &amp;ldquo;backyard&amp;rdquo; is uttered indicates that there is more to what I am saying than could be gathered from referring to a dictionary. In fact, if I were to strictly interpret this statement according to the lexical meaning, what some people mean by &lt;em&gt;literal meaning&lt;/em&gt;, then this would generate an interpretive error as well as an implausible meaning for my statement. How could &lt;em&gt;the world&lt;/em&gt; be my backyard?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In his writing on metaphor, Davidson insists that in interpreting metaphors people, in fact, identify the falsehood involved in the lexical reading of a metaphorical statement (e.g., &amp;ldquo;The world &lt;em&gt;is not&lt;/em&gt; a backyard!&amp;quot;) and then move onto more productive interpretations, metaphorical ones, in this case. While this two-step process may, in fact, occur in particular circumstances, I think it is too strong to assume that it is a necessity. There are some cases where metaphorical/creative/loose interpretations are assumed from the start, such as in the case of reading a poem or in the case of someone using a metaphor that is &lt;em&gt;nearly&lt;/em&gt; dead. It is also important to note that people can easily move from &amp;lsquo;metaphorical&amp;rsquo; to &amp;lsquo;literal&amp;rsquo; interpretations seamlessly. For example, while I may use &amp;ldquo;backyard&amp;rdquo; metaphorically to indicate &amp;ldquo;the world&amp;rdquo; in a specific context, there will likely be cases where the lexical meaning will be more relevant. If I say, &amp;ldquo;My dog is in the backyard,&amp;rdquo; one would hope that I am saying it is in an &lt;em&gt;actual&lt;/em&gt; backyard and not loose in the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;social-practices-as-generative-constraints&#34;&gt;Social practices as generative constraints&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In generating meaning, language-use relies on, but is not &lt;em&gt;determined&lt;/em&gt; by lexical meaning and other linguistic standards. It is possible to imagine situations in which syntax and grammar are distorted, intentionally or otherwise, but an utterance still results in the successful communication of an intended meaning. So we can say with confidence that pragmatic factors also play a large role. While there are a number of ways to break these factors down, I will emphasize the primacy of &lt;em&gt;social practices&lt;/em&gt;. While we may refer to indexicals––words or phrases that &lt;em&gt;demand&lt;/em&gt; filling by contextual ingredients, such as time and place––as standalone pragmatic factors of language-use, there is an important sense in which these rely on underlying social practices to be effective. For example, if I say, &amp;ldquo;&lt;em&gt;She&lt;/em&gt; is being silly &lt;em&gt;today&lt;/em&gt;,&amp;rdquo; the &amp;ldquo;she&amp;rdquo; and  &amp;ldquo;today&amp;rdquo; in the statement must be filled in with contextually salient information. In this case, &amp;ldquo;she&amp;rdquo; refers to my dog and &amp;ldquo;today&amp;rdquo; refers to the day that this statement was actually uttered. I could easily make the same statement in a different context and &lt;em&gt;mean&lt;/em&gt; something completely different. Although there aren&amp;rsquo;t specific rules that specify what indexical expressions &lt;em&gt;point to&lt;/em&gt;, our social practices provide us with guidance (e.g., conventions, habits, activities, and/or rates of success in determining meaning). Therefore, while there is use in distinguishing between pragmatic factors, there is an important sense in which social practices underpin these, at least partially.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Social practices are, of course, not &lt;em&gt;sui generis&lt;/em&gt;, but dependent on a number of contingent factors, such as the environment, biology, and history. Moreover, a given social practice, may be dependent on another or many other social practices. The social practice of &amp;lsquo;playing poker&amp;rsquo; hinges on a variety of other social practices, such as those leading to the production of cards and so forth. Furthermore, while a social practice must involve intentional actions, the social practice itself may not be practiced intentionally––although in some cases it may have been originated through an intentional act. Finally, social practices necessarily entail relations between people. They often, if not always, entail other non-human relations (e.g., to the natural world, the built environment, etc&amp;hellip;).  In Marxism, there is an emphasis on &lt;em&gt;social relations&lt;/em&gt;, which may be seen as a way of situating social practices within an interconnected and interdependent whole––sometimes referred to as a &lt;em&gt;totality&lt;/em&gt;––that makes up a given society or system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Language-use is dependent on social practices, which are themselves dependent upon a variety of factors. Importantly, they are dependent on an interdependent system of social relations, which although involving intentional action is not itself dependent upon the specific intention &lt;em&gt;to undertake&lt;/em&gt; the practices implied by a given system of social relations. While social practices provide language-use with &lt;em&gt;necessary&lt;/em&gt; guidance to generate meaning in the first place, they do so by &lt;em&gt;constraining&lt;/em&gt; the way in which language-use expresses meaning. Flaunting social practices means risking a failure of meaning. While a metaphor may &lt;em&gt;land&lt;/em&gt; it does not do so necessarily––the existence of languishing poets is a case in point.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;language-use-and-the-critique-of-capitalism&#34;&gt;Language-use and the critique of capitalism&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In &lt;em&gt;Capital&lt;/em&gt;, vol.1 Marx states &amp;ldquo;&lt;em&gt;To the producers, therefore, the social relations between their private labours appear as what they are&lt;/em&gt;, i.e. they do not appear as direct social relations between persons in their work, but rather as material [dinglich] relations between persons and social relations between things&amp;rdquo; (emphasis added). This is often taken to mean that people in capitalism are exhibiting &amp;ldquo;false-consciousness,&amp;rdquo; that they are mistaken in their understanding of the &lt;em&gt;actual&lt;/em&gt; social relations. However, as noted by many, this portrayal of the situation gets something &lt;em&gt;very wrong&lt;/em&gt;. People aren&amp;rsquo;t &lt;em&gt;mistaken&lt;/em&gt; about their views of social and material relations under capitalism. These &amp;ldquo;material relations between persons and social relations between things&amp;rdquo; are, in fact, the relations that drive peoples&#39; survival and demise. As Marx puts it, &amp;ldquo;they appear as what they are&amp;rdquo;! As one cannot flaunt the constraints on language use without risk, the stakes are even higher with the flaunting of social practices that generate your means of subsistence. While the particular social practices that amount to the given social relations are dependent upon and, therefore, appearances of, an more primary ontological substratum, these appearances, better viewed as &lt;em&gt;expressions&lt;/em&gt; of the substratum, have a &lt;em&gt;grip&lt;/em&gt; on the reality of those living them. Put differently, we have to &lt;em&gt;live through&lt;/em&gt; these appearances. It is disingenuous to suggest that people are &lt;em&gt;merely&lt;/em&gt; confused and could decide to behave differently.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That said, it should not be overlooked that there &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; a mistake to which everyone in capitalism is susceptible: the error of viewing the &amp;lsquo;inverted&amp;rsquo; social and material relations of capitalism as an &lt;em&gt;unmediated Given&lt;/em&gt;, a natural fact. This explains, in part, the tendency in economics and sociology to tackle only the &lt;em&gt;products&lt;/em&gt; of these social relations (e.g., price, supply/demand, socio-economic status, and education), rather than relations themselves. These products or facts are &lt;em&gt;&amp;lsquo;naturally&amp;rsquo;&lt;/em&gt; aligned with the specific practices that make up capitalist social relations. In turn, by referencing such facts, the social practices undergirding language-use are not put to under strain. Even in the case of &amp;lsquo;discovering&amp;rsquo; an economic &amp;lsquo;fact&amp;rsquo;––supply and demand, let&amp;rsquo;s say––this does not break with the pragmatics of language-use, those constrained by capitalist social relations, but rather &lt;em&gt;articulates&lt;/em&gt; them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since capitalist social relations are &lt;em&gt;treated&lt;/em&gt; as a Given, this means that any attempt to &lt;em&gt;critique&lt;/em&gt; such relations will be going against the grain of the relations themselves. When one critiques capitalism, one is faced with a problem comparable to using indexicals to &lt;em&gt;point at&lt;/em&gt; things in a non-standard fashion: &amp;ldquo;When &lt;em&gt;I&lt;/em&gt; say &amp;lsquo;it&amp;rsquo; I do not mean the thing &amp;lsquo;it&amp;rsquo; usually means, but the thing that underlies &lt;em&gt;the thing &amp;lsquo;it&amp;rsquo; usually means&lt;/em&gt;.&amp;rdquo; Critique thus necessarily has a greater risk of failure in comparison to language-use in the idiom of classical and neo-classical economics––the realm of &amp;lsquo;immediate&amp;rsquo; social facts that takes this so-called immediacy as the warrant for their legitimacy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The difficulty in critique lies in mediating the apparent immediacy of capitalist social relations. Like an excessively esoteric metaphor, critique adds another step or layer to interpretation that must be taken into account––a direct attack on the principle of parsimony. More than difficult to undertake or absorb, critique proposes an idea that is at diametrically at odds with what is Given. It suggests that our words and concepts are, as Adorno states, &amp;ldquo;entwined with a non-conceptual whole.&amp;rdquo; Thus the challenge posed by critique comes across as a delusion––a gloomy misapprehension. Beyond this, while we are living through capitalism, the critique of capitalism must be undertaken with the linguistic social-practices &lt;em&gt;of capitalism&lt;/em&gt; that form us. Despite &lt;em&gt;attempts&lt;/em&gt; to do otherwise, if we critique capitalism, we are necessarily doing so from within. Immanent critique, in this sense, means dissolving the Givenness of capitalist social relations.
The apparent immediacy of capitalist social relations transforms what is, in fact, part of the subject––capitalist social relations––into a seeming object. Objectified social relations do not &lt;em&gt;pass&lt;/em&gt; as social relations, but as objects. The act of critique must, therefore, negate the negation of the objectified subject by pointing to the non-conceptual ground of capitalist social-relations, social relations as such. It must disclose how the &amp;lsquo;object&amp;rsquo; is a subject.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The one advantage provided by the objectification of the subject &lt;em&gt;for critique&lt;/em&gt; is that it is a standard feature of language-use to engage with the world, the object. Yet, as I said at the start of this post, despite a connection existing between the subject and object, there must also be a distinction. This distinction implies that language cannot contain the world as a whole, on pain of denying the world as such. Therefore, the necessary gap between subject and object provides a similar gap between &lt;em&gt;objectified&lt;/em&gt; social relations and the subject. The problem of the Giveness of capitalist social relations for critique also seems to &lt;em&gt;potentially&lt;/em&gt; provide its solution. In my view, Wilfrid Sellars&#39; understanding of the &amp;ldquo;scientific image&amp;rdquo; and language provides resources for exploiting this paradox in capitalist social relations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;sellars-and-the-scientific-image&#34;&gt;Sellars and the scientific image&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like Adorno, Sellars argues there is an ontological surfeit that cannot be fully captured conceptually (i.e., through language-use). There must be a distinction between mind and world. Although he espouses naturalism, which may seem &lt;em&gt;prima facie&lt;/em&gt; at odds with Adorno, Sellars does not adopt a reductionist approach to science. For Sellars, certain normative concepts are irreducible to non-normative, scientific ones. Tied to his brand of naturalism, Sellars is also aligned with Adorno in terms of viewing appearances in a Hegelian light, as more than &lt;em&gt;mere&lt;/em&gt; illusions––as objectively existing expressions of an &amp;lsquo;essence&amp;rsquo; or substratum that have practical effects on our social practices.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sellars makes an important distinction between the &amp;ldquo;manifest image&amp;rdquo; and the &amp;ldquo;scientific image.&amp;rdquo; Given that the manifest image also includes refined scientific thinking, the terminology is slightly misleading. Very briefly, the manifest image is the image in which humans first &amp;lsquo;encounter themselves&amp;rsquo;––when humans first &lt;em&gt;became&lt;/em&gt; &amp;lsquo;human&amp;rsquo;. In essence, it is the ground of conceptual thinking. However, as Sellars notes, conceptual thinking in the manifest image is dominated by viewing the things in its ontology as &lt;em&gt;persons&lt;/em&gt;, including non-human objects. Of course, Sellars doesn&amp;rsquo;t think that humans in the manifest image treat non-human objects and phenomena as &lt;em&gt;actual&lt;/em&gt; people, but rather that the non-human world can be &lt;em&gt;explained&lt;/em&gt; using normative and intentional concepts––concepts that hinge on standards of correctness/incorrectness. For Sellars, a deficiency of the manifest image is that it presupposes that the world cannot be explained outside of normative language-use. In fact, there is a sense in which the manifest images implies the full intelligibility of the world, since the world is, in principle conceptually articulated in normative terms. However, for Sellars, the ontological surfeit that escapes the grasp of normative concepts, gives rise to contradictions in the manifest image, which leads to its evolution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In contrast, the scientific image involves the &amp;ldquo;postulation of imperceptible entities, and principles pertaining to them, to explain the behaviour of perceptible things.&amp;rdquo; The go-to example of this type of concept-use is theoretical physics, such as when forces are postulated to explain the movement of bodies. The scientific image must, by necessity, use concepts normatively in the sense that even descriptive assertions are subject to normative standards of correctness––the concept-use and linguistic practices of the scientific image arise from the manifest image, after all. But unlike the manifest image, it attempts explanation in a non-intentional and non-normative manner. It postulates &lt;em&gt;non-person-like&lt;/em&gt; forces, objects, and phenomena to provide non-normative explanations, even including explanations of normative and conceptual aspects of our reality (e.g., how evolutions is often &lt;em&gt;clumsily&lt;/em&gt; used to explain all human behaviour).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The scientific image is not &lt;em&gt;sui generis&lt;/em&gt;, but necessarily arises out of and draws its resources from the manifest image. Conversely, the scientific image&amp;rsquo;s explanations are taken up by the manifest image. As Dionysis Christias argues in his paper &amp;ldquo;The Non-Conceptual Dimension of Social Mediation: Toward a Materialist Aufhebung of Hegel&amp;rdquo; (2019, International Journal of Philosophical Studies, 27:3), there is a dialectical relationship between the manifest and scientific images.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-scientific-image-as-the-negation-of-the-negation&#34;&gt;The scientific image as the negation of the negation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To reiterate, capitalist social relations &amp;ldquo;do not appear as direct social relations between persons in their work, but rather as material relations between persons and social relations between things.&amp;rdquo; It is then fair to say that while these relations are objectified, they are nevertheless viewed as &lt;em&gt;person-like&lt;/em&gt;. While the &lt;em&gt;social relations between things&lt;/em&gt; are not &lt;em&gt;mere&lt;/em&gt; appearances, their understanding as objectified Givens nonetheless hinges on treating &lt;em&gt;things&lt;/em&gt; as primarily being subject to the normative descriptions of the manifest image. Therefore, despite being often characterized as a &lt;em&gt;scientific&lt;/em&gt; measure of human activity, it is more apt to describe economics as a predominant manifest image &amp;lsquo;explanation&amp;rsquo; of the world. The &amp;lsquo;facts&amp;rsquo; economics locates and the analysis it undertakes remains locked in the manifest image.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite the leeriness one may feel in approaching Sellars&#39; use of the term &amp;lsquo;&lt;em&gt;scientific&lt;/em&gt;&amp;rsquo; in his conception of the scientific image, the critique of capitalism must &lt;em&gt;necessarily&lt;/em&gt; be scientific according to his description &lt;em&gt;in order to be effective&lt;/em&gt;. Like Adorno, Sellars views the necessity of reaching outside the normative constraints of manifest image language-use, to engage in the scientific image, in order to critique and hopefully &lt;em&gt;change&lt;/em&gt; the terms of the manifest image itself. In &lt;em&gt;Capital&lt;/em&gt; Marx does just this. By postulating &amp;lsquo;invisible&amp;rsquo;, but objective phenomena, such as value and fetishism, he is turning the manifest image against itself, locating non-normative forces that drive our normative social practices. In this way, Adorno&amp;rsquo;s critique of capitalism can be seen as an extension and refinement of Marx&amp;rsquo;s project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Capitalism&amp;rsquo;s negation of the subject––turning mediated social relations into an apparent Given object––must be negated by appeal to the non-normative and non-conceptual. Paradoxically, this must be done using the linguistic resources of the manifest image itself. Critique is necessarily imminent to social practices of language-use under capitalism. Like any novel use of language––metaphorical language-use or scientifically testing the objectivity of postulated force––there is a necessary risk. The metaphor may not land. A scientific hypothesis may be rejected. And critique may not dissolve the objectified appearance of capitalist social relations. Regardless of these difficulties, we know that erecting a scientific image with the tools of the manifest image is possible. It has been done before. The trick with critique is to continue experimenting and finding ways of clarifying how the appearance of objectified social relations rest upon something else, that this appearance is subject and therefore subject to revision.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>