<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>science on Value Thing</title>
    <link>https://value-thing.github.io/tags/science/</link>
    <description>Value Thing (science)</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 27 Oct 2020 00:00:00 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
    <atom:link href="https://value-thing.github.io/tags/science/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>What I am talking about when I avoid talking about &#39;Marxism as a science&#39;, but still talk about Marxism as being scientific</title>
      <link>https://value-thing.github.io/post/scientificmarxism/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Oct 2020 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://value-thing.github.io/post/scientificmarxism/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-basic-questions&#34;&gt;The basic questions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When discussions about “Marxism as a science”(MS) pop up, they often involve equivocations between, on the one hand, the meaning of “science” and, on the other, the meaning of “Marxism.” While the latter equivocation is part and parcel of the ‘joys’ of being a Marxist, the former one &lt;em&gt;seems&lt;/em&gt; specific to the issue of MS and consequently more primary.&lt;!-- more --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some people take Marxism to be a science in the sense that it  operates like a natural science and targets similar phenomena. Sometimes, this view is ostensibly refined by specifying that Marxism operates like a “social science.”  Unfortunately, this latter move simply pushes back the question of “What is science and how is Marxism like it?” by an extra step. The question then becomes two questions “What is social science and how is Marxism like it?” and “What is science and how is social science like it?”  While this seems like a potentially useful endeavour in certain contexts, for the purposes of identifying MS , it merely adds an assumption that needs to be investigated prior to the original question. Put differently, we should be able to figure out how Marxism is like a science without also knowing how social science is like science.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since the &lt;em&gt;rejection&lt;/em&gt; of MS hinges on the identification of criteria for &lt;em&gt;what counts as science&lt;/em&gt;, it must also wrestle with the question of “What is science and how is Marxism like it?”  This is means that a productive debate about whether Marxism is a science would first have to settle the more basic question “&lt;em&gt;What is science?&lt;/em&gt;”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Answering this question will also help ensure that we’re not speaking at cross-purposes in a debate over the status of MS. For example, let’s assume that A argues that ‘science = falsifiable empirical research’ and B argues that ‘science = any systematized and self-correcting body of knowledge.’ Even if A and B both agree (or disagree) with the proposition that “Marxism is a science,” there is no  &lt;em&gt;substantive&lt;/em&gt; agreement between the two. The only agreement generated in this case is that &lt;em&gt;according to their respective stipulations of science, A and B do (or do not) view Marxism as a science&lt;/em&gt;.  A and B’s stipulations may not only be different, but in conflict––once again raising the question, “&lt;em&gt;What is science&lt;/em&gt;?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;why-i-will-not-tell-you-what-science-is&#34;&gt;Why I will not tell you what science is&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don’t have the time, the expertise, nor the will to tackle the question of what it is that makes a given practice &amp;ldquo;science,&amp;rdquo; but it is a worthwhile one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moreover,  I don’t think the answer to this question can be cashed out on its own for significant gains, aside from rhetorical ones––which is not nothing, but also not my concern &lt;em&gt;at this very moment&lt;/em&gt;.  Once we have an answer to the question “What is science?” we still have to figure out the original question, “Is Marxism a science?”, which itself hinges on knowing what Marxism is.  My view is that once we figure out what is meant by ‘Marxism’, specifically what types of things ‘Marxism’ allows one to do, the question of whether it is a science becomes largely a terminological and rhetorical issue.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;why-i-will-not-tell-you-what-marxism-is&#34;&gt;Why I will not tell you what Marxism is&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Originally, I made the case that the question “What is science?” is more basic than “What is Marxism?”, but now I am arguing that the former question is a bit of a sideshow, given that the question “Is Marxism a science?” is overshadowed by the pragmatic implications of something qualifying as ‘Marxism’  (i.e., what Marxism allows you to do).  Now, to confuse things further, to bring us back to the beginning, &lt;em&gt;I will not even bother with telling you what Marxism is.&lt;/em&gt; While I think  there is something identifiably Marxist in all honest expressions of Marxism, I’m almost positive that this common property may simply be the fact that Marxist authors refer to Marx or other Marxists in a loosely, but not uniformly or even overwhelmingly, positive fashion (e.g., Analytical Marxism vs. Western Marxism).  This commonality is a mere triviality that generates other trivialities and, occasionally, these are put forward as insightful : “There isn’t &lt;em&gt;a&lt;/em&gt; Marxism, there are &lt;em&gt;Marxisms&lt;/em&gt;!” and “Marxists  seem to only spend their time arguing with one another!” Moving on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;doing-things-with-marxism&#34;&gt;Doing things with ‘Marxism’&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are instances where the connection between Marxism and science does seem salient, where &lt;em&gt;Marxism is behaving like a science, in the sense that Marxism is fulfilling the criteria that have been stipulated for what counts as science&lt;/em&gt;.  In his book, &lt;em&gt;Continuity and Rupture&lt;/em&gt; (2016), J. Moufawad-Paul outlines how Marxism-Leninism-Maoism, under his conception of MLM and science, &lt;em&gt;does just this&lt;/em&gt;.  This is no trivial accomplishment.  Although I find his argument compelling, I will not delve into the details, given that this would bring us back to the &lt;em&gt;basic questions&lt;/em&gt; that I am intent on avoiding. Regardless of his argument’s merits, what Moufawad-Paul does in his book is to show how a particular conception of Marxism &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; science, allows one to &lt;em&gt;do certain things&lt;/em&gt;, including practical things in the world.  Moufawad-Paul is not merely mulling over the basic questions––providing nuance and specificity to the relevant definitions––but  &lt;em&gt;showing&lt;/em&gt; how the conceptions he presents make a practical difference. While Moufawad-Paul’s argument for MLM is constructed as hinging on it being a &lt;em&gt;science&lt;/em&gt; of revolution, in my view the tight link between science and Marxism that he argues for is perhaps better seen as a by-product of the practices and inferences that his conception generates.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If a conception does what it says it does, which is to make a practical difference, then what difference does it make to label this conception “a science”?  It largely seems to be a compliment that we are paying to something because it does what it says it does. Questions of whether the connection between a particular conception of MS and the natural sciences is literal or metaphorical or whether MS is more akin to a social science are secondary to the question of what sorts of practices, inferences, and effects this conception affords. It seems to me that often times what we do when we say we are putting forward MS is opening ourselves to debating the &lt;em&gt;basic questions&lt;/em&gt;. Questions that are likely fruitful, but also secondary and highly contentious.  That said, maybe I am just succumbing  to the influence of the perennial &lt;em&gt;Show Don’t Tell&lt;/em&gt; mantra of writing.  And, if this is the case, I must also be partial to the &lt;em&gt;Do As I Say, Not As I Do&lt;/em&gt; school of thought.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;marxism-and-the-scientific-image&#34;&gt;Marxism and the scientific image&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having argued that MS is an issue of secondary importance, I also––perhaps paradoxically––believe that it is crucial for Marxism to be “scientific” in the Sellarsian sense of being a project that is  situated in the &lt;em&gt;scientific image&lt;/em&gt; rather than the &lt;em&gt;manifest image&lt;/em&gt;.  As sketched out in the previous post, the difference between the manifest image and the scientific image can be roughly glossed as the difference between normative and intentionally-oriented &lt;em&gt;evaluations&lt;/em&gt;, on the one hand, and non-normative and non-intentional &lt;em&gt;explanations&lt;/em&gt;, on the other. Although the scientific image emerges from the manifest image, neither image is reducible to the other. In fact, paradoxically, through its postulation of “imperceptible entities, and principles pertaining to them, to explain the behaviour of perceptible things” (e.g., natural selection, class struggle, etc…),  the scientific image can, in fact, explain how aspects of the manifest arose in the first place .&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In &lt;em&gt;explaining&lt;/em&gt; the real and effective &lt;em&gt;appearances&lt;/em&gt; of capitalism by identifying “imperceptible entities,” which include value, fetishism, and social relations (etc…), Marx’s approach to the critique of political economy seems to fall in the scientific image.  Other aspects are not so easy to square with this view. Even disregarding the potentially non-scientific image aspects of Marx, this &lt;em&gt;does not&lt;/em&gt; mean, even in the  Sellarsian idiom, that specific expressions of Marxism are “scientific” in the way most people intend when they appeal to MS.  Rather, Sellars was careful to note that the manifest image was not “pre-scientific”, but included what would be considered science. For him, what counts as &lt;em&gt;scientific&lt;/em&gt; in the sense of belonging to the scientific image is the prioritization of &lt;em&gt;explanations&lt;/em&gt;  that use non-normative and non-intentional concepts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, even if I am willing to say with confidence that Marxism is scientific ––albeit &lt;em&gt;in a Sellarsian sense&lt;/em&gt;––this does not entitle me, for now, to proclaim Marxism as a science (in the unspecified way most people mean).  I hope that this  view amounts to more than word games, that the distinction between “science” and “scientific image” is more than simply a matter of hedging my bets or having it both ways. So far,  using Sellars to read Marx has allowed me to approach Marx in immediately fruitful ways, but this could obviously change once I do more work and actually put some of these ideas to the test.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>