<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>electoralism on Value Thing</title>
    <link>https://value-thing.github.io/tags/electoralism/</link>
    <description>Value Thing (electoralism)</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 30 Oct 2020 00:00:00 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
    <atom:link href="https://value-thing.github.io/tags/electoralism/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Quick thoughts on voting</title>
      <link>https://value-thing.github.io/post/quickthoughtsonvoting/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Oct 2020 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://value-thing.github.io/post/quickthoughtsonvoting/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I do not presume to have a knockdown argument &lt;em&gt;for or against&lt;/em&gt; voting in national elections. Approaching voting as an act that can be evaluated in isolation, seems to raise more questions than it resolves. For example, by looking at voting alone, it becomes difficult to confirm or deny that &lt;em&gt;Your Vote Is Important&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;This Election Is (The Most) Important&lt;/em&gt;. On the one hand, in tight races a single vote seems to be become undeniably important, in some sense. On the other, in the bigger picture a vote is simply one among many. If a single vote is deciding the election how do we pick which one is the deciding vote? If a party loses by a single vote and A and B were intending to vote for the losing party, but didn’t, is A or is B responsible for the party losing? Are they both? Or maybe it is the party itself that is responsible, since it was unable to create the motivation required for A or B to vote in the first place.  &lt;em&gt;These are the questions that I want to avoid.&lt;/em&gt; &lt;!-- more --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;recipes-for-an-individual-act&#34;&gt;Recipes for an individual act&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Relatively depoliticized campaigns to &lt;em&gt;Get Out The Vote&lt;/em&gt; and more politicized “movements” that spend significant resources on getting their members to vote tend to downplay or misapprehend what a vote is. Each of these approaches to voting can be seen, at least in part, as making up the &lt;em&gt;recipe&lt;/em&gt; that leads a given individual to vote––either to vote &lt;em&gt;in general&lt;/em&gt; or to vote for a specific party/candidate.  However, once an individual gets to the ballot box and votes, this recipe is largely abstracted from the vote itself.   Whatever social, economic, ideological, and/or political motivations go into the vote recipe, in the &lt;em&gt;act of voting&lt;/em&gt; these are boiled down to a singularly political act––more of an abstract ode to ‘citizenship’ than the expression of a struggle or ‘movement’.  Whatever perspective goes into casting a vote, it is the perspective of the bodies that administer the terrain on which elections play out that matters. This perspective will not and &lt;em&gt;cannot&lt;/em&gt; directly apprehend a single vote as anything but an individual act.  Voting, under these circumstances, becomes analogous to accepting the terms for an unfair fight in which the voter is at a disadvantage. This is the form that voting takes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-vampire-state&#34;&gt;The vampire state&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;CEOs, hedge fund managers, and landlords don’t need to rely solely on votes to get their objectives achieved. This would be ineffective and likely disastrous for capital accumulation.  Regardless of whether they know it &lt;em&gt;as such&lt;/em&gt;, a vote is transaction in which concrete economic/social/ideological/political concerns are translated into abstract political concerns. The exchange rate on such a transaction does not favour &lt;em&gt;any&lt;/em&gt; voter.  However, the vote exchange rate in a capitalist state is especially unfavourable to those outside of the bourgeoisie. Without delving into how one conceives of the state (e.g., autonomous, epiphenomenal, instrumental, etc…), a capitalist state must, well…somehow sustain capitalism. Thus, when one’s voting recipe is exchanged for a vote, becoming an individualized and abstract political act, it is translated into the terms of the capitalist state.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While a vote may be aggregated with others as a representation of particular ‘interests’––extrapolating from exit poll data, for example–– each of these interests is nevertheless abstracted from its original concrete and contextualized manifestations.  These &lt;em&gt;interest positions&lt;/em&gt; are mapped onto the existing economic/social/legal/ideological/political terrain of the state. Needless to say, anything like class struggle largely disappears and is replaced with the objective &lt;em&gt;appearance&lt;/em&gt; of an electorate with competing interest positions that must be realigned and ideally harmonized––this necessarily sometimes involves a degree of compromise and change––with the existing terrain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;not-nothing&#34;&gt;Not nothing&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It would be hyperbolic to say the above amounts to a &lt;em&gt;refutation of voting&lt;/em&gt;. Firstly, as I said, I think the question of voting &lt;em&gt;as such&lt;/em&gt; doesn’t say much about anything. It is abstract question about an act of abstraction. Therefore, my interest does not lie with a rejection of voting in itself. Secondly, notwithstanding the above, the &lt;em&gt;abstraction of voting&lt;/em&gt; takes place in a real context.  The potential gains of participating in the abstraction are real and may, in significant ways, ameliorate the lives of voters. Such gains cannot be simply discounted on the basis that they are the result of adopting the terms of an unfair fight.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That said––and this is an obvious point to most––if a vote is to be cast, it should be cast with knowledge of the abstraction that takes place.  While this knowledge doesn’t amount to much on its own, it can &lt;em&gt;and does&lt;/em&gt; lead struggles to look beyond &lt;em&gt;the struggle to vote&lt;/em&gt;.  This type of political education may need to reassess the relation and tension between proximate, often critical if not necessary, material gains and the challenges required to achieve the overcoming of the present––flexible–– &lt;em&gt;form&lt;/em&gt; of the capitalist state.  Through such analysis it may be possible to identify the manner in which material gains coincide with the establishment of conditions more favourable to class struggle. However, achieving  the benefits of the welfare state &lt;em&gt;without fragmenting the working class to the overall benefit of capital accumulation&lt;/em&gt; is a difficult needle to thread, one that has been debated for decades.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This implies that political education to be political &lt;em&gt;cannot&lt;/em&gt; be simply about how to organize the masses to vote one way or another.  It must rather tackle the question of how to avoid the exchange of social + economic +political concerns for purely political ones framed by the existing state, how to set the terms so that the fight is at least &lt;em&gt;less unfair&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>